Well, I'm not convinced that the work is as
urgent as this report suggests, so perhaps
we should…
Oh come on, the building is practically falling
down!
Sorry Lin, I don't think Tan had finished.
We'll get to you in a minute.
Sorry.
As I was saying, perhaps we should get a second
opinion before we spend any money.
Thank you Tan. What's your opinion Walter?
Well, as far as I'm concerned, it's a question
of safety. So I think we should go ahead.
Are you suggesting that someone could get
hurt?
In my opinion, yes. If you ask me, there is
a serious risk of an accident. And it's not
a recent problem.
Are you implying we should have done something
earlier?
Much earlier. It's a real concern.
Hear hear!
In that case, I agree. We should do something
now.
I think so too.
Thank you Walter. Well, if there's no,
Excuse me Madame Chairperson.
Yes Barbara.
What about the problem with parking? There
were no places again this morning.
Maybe if you got to work on time.
All comments through the chair if you don't
mind Walter. Parking isn't on the agenda for
this meeting. Perhaps you could suggest it
for our next meeting Barbara. Well, if there's
no more discussion, we'll put it to a vote.
Hear hear!
Today we're looking again at meetings. In
meetings, especially formal meetings, it's
important to keep the discussion relevant,
and to the point. So we're looking at some
words and phrases that a Chairperson might
use to stop irrelevant discussion and interruptions.
We're also looking at ways of stating an opinion,
and agreeing or disagreeing.
First of all, notice how Tan states that he
doesn't agree with the report.
Well, I'm not convinced that the work is as
urgent as this report suggests.
Tan says, "I'm not convinced." He means he
disagrees with the report. But by saying he's
not convinced - he is leaving himself open
to another point of view.
Let's look at some phrases you can use to
express disagreement.
I'm afraid I'm not convinced.
I don't entirely agree.
I'm not sure about that.
I can't agree with you there.
I don't think that's quite correct.
Notice that all of these ways of disagreeing
are polite. If you use stronger terms of disagreement,
it can sound rude, or argumentative.
Well, I'm not convinced that the work is as
urgent as this report suggests, so perhaps.
Don't be ridiculous!
Excuse me?
When disagreeing, the speaker normally also
gives a reason for their opinion, and may
use an expression showing that it is their
opinion. Listen to Walter.
Well, as far as I'm concerned, it's a question
of safety. So I think we should go ahead.
Are you suggesting that someone could get
hurt?
In my opinion, es.
Let's practise some phrases you can use to
introduce your opinion about something.
In my opinion
As far as I'm concerned
If you ask me
The way I see it is this.
And of course you can simply state, "I think"
or "I believe".
Notice that Tan asks for clarification of
the point Walter makes. He wants to make sure
he understands what Walter is saying.
Let's look at some ways of seeking clarification,
and checking understanding. Practise these
with Tan.
Are you suggesting that someone could get
hurt?
Are you saying that someone could get hurt?
Do you mean someone could get hurt?
Are you implying that someone could get hurt?
One of the roles of the Chairperson is to
make sure everyone gets to have their say.
All discussion should go through the chair
- that is, people talk to the Chairperson,
not to each other directly. So the Chairperson
sometimes has to interrupt, or stop someone
from speaking. Let's see how Denise does this.
Well, I'm not convinced that the work is as
urgent as this report suggests, so perhaps.
Oh come on, the building is practically falling
down!
Sorry Lin, I don't think Tan had finished.
We'll get to you in a minute.
Sorry.
By saying, "I don't think Tan had finished",
Denise is politely telling Lin that she shouldn't
interrupt, and Lin apologises. But what should
you do if someone keeps trying to interrupt?
So perhaps,
Oh come on - the building is practically falling
down!
Sorry Lin, I don't think Tan had finished.
We'll get to you in a minute.
Well it's obvious.
Yes, but we do need to hear everyone's views
on this.
Let's just vote on it.
All in good time Lin. Please go on Tan.
Notice that the language the chairperson uses
is always polite, but firm. She uses 'sorry'
'thank you' and 'please' as a way of respecting
the other members of the committee, although
she is in charge.
On the other hand, there is a time factor
- it may be necessary to cut people short.
and furthermore, if we look more closely at
some of the estimates, we can see,
Excuse me - sorry Tan, perhaps we should move
on.
I'm nearly finished.
Yes but we do have to keep an eye on the time.
Perhaps we can come back to that point later.
I think it's quite important.
It is important, but I think it's more important
we hear everyone's views on this. Barbara?
There were two key phrases used to stop Tan
from sending everyone to sleep. The first
one, "perhaps we should move on" is phrased
as a suggestion but it is said in a firm way,
with a falling intonation at the end.
Practise with me:
Perhaps we should move on.
This falling intonation makes it a more definite
statement, rather than a suggestion.
The second one was put as a reason for moving
on - that time is short. Nnotice the emphasis
on the word 'do', and practise after me:
We do have to keep an eye on the time.
Remember we said the discussion has to be
relevant. What do we do if someone makes an
irrelevant comment?
What about the problem with parking. There
were no places again this morning.
Maybe if you got to work on time.
All comments through the chair if you don't
mind Walter. Parking isn't on the agenda for
this meeting. Perhaps you could suggest it
for our next meeting Barbara.
When Walter makes a comment directly to Barbara,
Denise says:
All comments through the Chair if you don't
mind.
This is a way of reminding Walter of correct
meeting procedure. "All comments through the
Chair" means he must speak to the meeting,
not directly to one person at the table. Denise
suggests that, "Parking isn't on the agenda
for this meeting". But so that Barbara doesn't
feel bad, she suggests it could be discussed
at another time.
Finally, we've looked at disagreeing, Let's
look at ways of agreeing with a point.
Are you implying we should have done something
earlier?
Much earlier. It's a real concern.
Hear hear!
Well, in that case, I agree - we should do
something now.
I think so too.
Agreeing is simpler than disagreeing, as you
don't have to state a reason. Repeat these
phrases after me:
I agree
In that case, I agree.
I'll go along with you.
I couldn't agree more.
That's right.
I concur.
Absolutely!
Let's review some of the other important expressions
we've looked at in today's episode.
I'm afraid I'm not convinced.
Are you suggesting that someone could get
hurt?
I can't quite agree with you there.
As far as I'm concerned, it's a question of
safety.
Perhaps we should move on.
We do have to keep an eye on the time.
When giving opinions in a meeting, it's important
to use phrases such as 'in my opinion', 'from
my point of view' or 'I think', instead of
just stating your opinions as facts. This
is respectful of other people who may have
different views.
But when you strongly agree with something
someone else says, you can say 'Hear Hear!'
That's all for today - see you next time on
The Business of English.